<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="balisage-1-5.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="style/balisage-author.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="style/balisage-proceedings-html.xsl"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>Synthesis and Sustainability: The Evolution of Markup and Toolsets in the Women Writers
    Project</title>
  <info>
    <abstract>
      <para>In 1988, the Women Writers Project (WWP) started out on its very long history of working
        with markup systems. In 1999, the WWP began working with XML publication tools as well. In
        both cases, markup and tools, the WWP has treated the work as an active research
        undertaking: not only seeking to build a stable, sustainable working system, but also
        keeping pace with new developments and exploring their implications for research on early
        women’s writing. The intertwined history and co-evolution of these two sets of practices
        within the WWP’s nearly 40 years of work thus far can contribute a valuable perspective on
        the history of scholarly usage of markup in the humanities. This paper will explore the
        evolution of the WWP’s theory and practice of markup, from its pre-TEI origins to our
        present-day usage; as well as the evolution of the project’s publication systems, from its
        first forays into digital publication through DynaWeb to our planned implementation of a
        static-site framework that responds to the recommendations of the Endings Principles. We
        will also consider the reciprocal pressure that tools and markup exert on each other, and
        the nuanced ways in which markup responds to the changing intellectual paradigms proposed by
        successive generations of tools and technologies (and vice versa).</para>
    </abstract>
    <author>
      <personname>
        <firstname>Julia</firstname>
        <surname>Flanders</surname>
      </personname>
      <personblurb><!-- Julia blurb -->
        <para>Julia Flanders is the Director of the Women Writers Project and Director of the
          Northeastern University Library’s Digital Scholarship Group.</para>
      </personblurb>
      <affiliation>
        <orgname>Northeastern University</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <personname>
        <firstname>Ash</firstname>
        <surname>Clark</surname>
      </personname>
      <personblurb>
        <para>Ash Clark (e/em/eir or they/them) serves as XML Applications Developer for the Women Writers Project and the Digital Scholarship Group. Ash uses XQuery, XSLT, and XML databases to create data-gathering tools, generate metadata, and serve out websites. Eir current focus is on designing sites that are easily maintainable and accessible to all kinds of users.</para>
      </personblurb>
      <affiliation>
        <orgname>Northeastern University</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
  </info>
  <!-- Julia: backstory and roadmap for the paper 
       First mention of TEI will need a brief gloss
    -->
  <note><para>The introduction to this paper will include a brief backstory on the history and mission of the WWP, and will signal the topics and issues this paper is going to focus on.</para></note>
  
  <section><!-- When editing, look for things to cut for brevity, conciseness -->
    <title>Evolution of the WWP’s theory and practice of markup</title>
    <para>The WWP’s earliest markup practices were anchored in typesetting tools: student encoders
      starting in 1988 used Waterloo Script to capture functional textual units and formatting
      details. This approach was not guided by an explicit theory of markup, but it did embody
      certain assumptions about the role that markup could play in representing primary source
      documents (still a somewhat novel role for markup at that time). The now fundamental idea that
      markup should emphasize semantics rather than solely formatting was already present in the
      ways that Waterloo Script supported the identification of textual components (headings,
      paragraphs, etc.) in a way that was separable from their appearance, and this was especially
      crucial for primary source materials whose actual appearance on the page might vary
      considerably from text to text. And although this first stage of the WWP’s practice did not at
      all anticipate what the TEI would come to be, it did lay a groundwork that was at least
      amenable to an eventual transition to the TEI once P1 and P2 were available to demonstrate
      what a more thoroughly semantic approach could look like.</para>
    <!-- @ Julia: In the paragraph below, it might help to focus on one example throughout, as a way to make the historical background more tangible and concrete. 0/O would make sense, since the sample encoding uses it. The other examples could be mentioned later, or put in a note or footnote. ~Ash -->
    <para>Paradoxically, however, some of the earliest encoding debates within the project concerned
      the representation of the appearance of the source, and specifically the question of whether a
      glyph in the source text should be represented using a character that resembles it visually,
      or represents it informationally. Examples include the numeral 1 (which in many older sources
      resembles a capital I and may even have been printed using that piece of type), the letters
      “u” and “n” (which when inverted are often indistinguishable from each other), and the
      characters for zero and capital O. The WWP’s thinking about these kinds of cases was shaped by
      concerns among humanities scholars about loss of information about the physical source, and a
      resulting desire for visual fidelity to the text. Seen from that perspective (and in the
      absence of Unicode), the use of a capital I to represent a numeral 1 could appear defensible
      on visual grounds. But very early on, the project identified that resemblance (unsurprisingly)
      as a fallacy—dependent on typeface and likely to lead to all sorts of future practical and
      conceptual problems. The idea of markup as a “digital facsimile” gave way quickly to the idea
      of markup as a more informational representation of document structure. The project continued
      to be concerned with ways of representing the material aspects of documents, with each encoded
      transcription derived from an identifiable physical copy, and capturing aspects of formatting
      and material structure. But the TEI model demonstrated how that could be done explicitly
      through the markup itself: for example, through the <code>@rend</code> attribute or through
      mechanisms like <code>&lt;sic></code>:</para>
    <figure>
      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;sic corr="O">0&lt;/sic></programlisting>
      <caption>
        <para>This <link xlink:href="https://tei-c.org/Vault/GL/P3/CO.htm#COEDCOR">P3-era TEI encoding</link> indicates that the typesetter used the zero character in error (or out of necessity). The transcriber indicates that the correct character is the captial letter “O”.</para>
      </caption>
    </figure>
    <!-- @ Julia: We could probably get some leverage out of Syd's early descriptions of rendition ladders, e.g. https://wwp.northeastern.edu/about/history/archive/training/old/p3guide.html "The TEI rend attribute: the Renditional Ladders solution". I especially like this bit:
        "There are two important things to keep in mind. The first is that we record renditional, not presentational information. Renditional refers to how the OT looks; this is in contrast to presentational, which refers to how the electronic text should be printed or presented — the two are often different. The second point is that renditional information is secondarily descriptive of an element, rather than being the element's most inherent quality. That is, like all information on attributes, renditional information is not the defining characteristic of an element. Otherwise we'd simply use tag names like <italic>, which conveys far less information about the meaning and structure of the document."
      ~Ash -->
    <para>The WWP’s early work on rendition ladders provided an opportunity to explore how far the
      material and visual properties of texts could be formalized for descriptive (rather than
      output) purposes.</para>
    <para>In the early days of the TEI in the 1990s, the WWP was a typical early adopter in two
      senses. With its mission of creating a large collection of early women’s writing in English,
      the project emphasized both comprehensiveness and the recovery of inaccessible materials. But
      these two goals proved over time to pull in different directions, as the evolution of the TEI
      as a <emphasis role="ital">scholarly</emphasis> technology revealed different ways for digital
      resources to function as research objects. The idea of creating reference corpora or
      comprehensive research collections was an early and significant driver for the TEI and is
      exemplified by projects like <link xlink:href="https://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/">Perseus</link>, <link xlink:href="https://artfl-project.uchicago.edu/">ARTFL</link>, and the early documentary editing projects that
      constituted the <link xlink:href="https://tei-c.org/activities/projects/model-editions-partnership-historical-editions-in-the-digital-age/">Model Editions Partnership</link>. Such efforts signalled the importance of data
      interoperability and of markup systems that could work towards that end: schemas that could
      strongly reinforce consistency and “conformance” and provide a clear model for tools to
      operate on. The WWP’s work was certainly animated to some degree by motivations towards
      interoperability; the project explored collaborative approaches to the encoding of personal
      names with several other projects focused on women’s writing, and placed a high value on
      following emerging standard practices when possible. But an important early element of the
      project’s mission was to treat early women’s writing and early printed books as potential
      sources of complication and resistance to standardization.</para>
    <para>With the release of TEI P5 in 2007, the function of customization changed fundamentally: no longer as
      a laborious way of departing from the standard, but as a more or less required aspect of using
      the Guidelines, a tool that was in everyone’s hands. 
      <!-- @Julia: I added the sentence and quote below to give fuller context for the P5 change; feel free to cut or munge. ~Ash -->
      As the “Design Principles” section of <xref linkend="teip5about"/> describes the shift:<blockquote>
        <para>In brief, the TEI Guidelines define a general-purpose encoding scheme which makes it possible to encode different views of text, possibly intended for different applications, serving the majority of scholarly purposes of text studies in the humanities. Because no predefined encoding scheme can possibly serve all research purposes, the TEI scheme is designed to facilitate both selection from a wide range of predefined markup choices, and the addition of new (non-TEI) markup options. By providing a formally verifiable means of extending the TEI recommendations, the TEI makes it simple for such user-identified modifications to be incorporated into future releases of these Guidelines as they evolve.</para>
      </blockquote> This shift coincided exactly with an
      increased visibility of “digital humanities” within traditional scholarly spaces, and an
      interest in interpretive and critical uses of data modeling. For the WWP, the question of
      where early women’s writing might depart from canonical or standard models shifted at this
      point to become: how does the modeling of early women’s writing constitute a scholarly
      argument about that writing? And, by extension, the project took an approach to pedagogy
      (through its encoding seminars) that asked participants to undertake TEI encoding as an
      exercise in scholarly interpretation and reciprocal communication, rather than an effort to
      follow an established model in a strictly conformant manner.</para>
    <para>Another crucial step in the evolution of the WWP’s use of markup—also connected with the
      release of TEI P5—was the availability of markup structures akin to linked open data: the
      ‘ographies and their relationship to the emergence of RDF and technologies like XPath that
      enabled linking to precise locations within XML documents. For the WWP, this launched a shift
      away from a sole emphasis on documents, to representing a larger universe of entities in which
      those documents are one meaningful component. The WWP had already begun using internal
      authority control to manage a database of persons referenced in WWP texts, starting in 1996
      with a formal keying system developed by Syd Bauman. In 2008 the WWP received an NEH Digital
      Humanities Start-up grant to explore the complexities of managing personographies in the
      context of early modern women’s writing (see <xref linkend="melson2010"/>). Over time, the WWP
      has developed systematic data on people (with particular emphasis on authors featured in Women Writers in Review and Women Writers in Context), texts (featured in Women Writers:
      Intertextual Networks), and even to some extent events (which are featured in timelines as
      part of Women Writers in Context). This work diversifies the role of markup for the WWP, going
      beyond modeling documents to creating data structures that are independent of documents but
      constitute an important contextualization mechanism for them.</para>
    <para>The final niche in the WWP’s evolving use of markup brings us full circle to the roots of
      SGML as a way of modeling data in which “text” faces Janus-like towards the domains of
      document and data and operates effectively in both spaces. Over time the WWP has found
      important uses for lightweight, systematic, highly consistent, “data-like” markup that
      anticipates interfaces that are focused on retrieval and analysis rather than on “reading” in
      the traditional sense (as in Women Writers Online’s presentation of primary sources). The
      project uses TEI for its encoding documentation, for the periodical review documents in Women
      Writers in Review, and for the essays in Women Writers in Context, and in all three cases the
      approach is minimalist and functionalist rather than being animated by a research-oriented
      philosophy of full textual representation (as in the WWP textbase).
      <note>
        <para>See <xref linkend="wwp-pubs"/> for more information on WWP publications.</para>
      </note>
      The markup of the textual
      content focuses on a selection of high-value features (such as element names or quotations)
      that are specifically relevant to the rhetorical context of the materials, and the metadata
      carries more of the burden of representing features of the content that will be valuable for
      retrieval. In the case of encoding documentation, that includes including topic keywords and
      an inventory of elements and attributes referenced. In the case of WWiR, it includes thematic
      keywords and an inventory of authors and texts mentioned in the review. Shifting these aspects
      of content into metadata (rather than tagging them in the running prose of the review or
      documentation entry) serves the pragmatic purpose of streamlining the encoding process, but it
      also acknowledges that these informational aspects are intended to function as retrieval hooks
      rather than as an activity of analysis or textual representation. In other words, it posits a
      different rhetorical framing for this information.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="evolution-of-toolsets" xreflabel="Evolution of Toolsets">
    <!-- Julia: look for screenshots of the various tools
        Ash: ask Syd too
      -->
    <title>Evolution of toolsets</title>
    <para>The WWP has had an unusually long history that traverses many generations of SGML and XML
      publication tools, and the project’s data has presented some valuable challenges and edge
      cases that have tested and revealed the limits of the tools it has used. The project’s main
      publication, Women Writers Online, has used four different platforms since its first
      publication in 1999:<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>DynaWeb: 1999–2006 (by 2004 this system was no longer supported)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Philologic: 2005–2012 (by 2012 this system would not run on a modern server)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem><!-- Ash: fire up old copy of XTF and get screenshots -->
          <para>An in-house, modular publication system served out of XTF: 2012–2025 (by 2019 XTF was
            getting harder to maintain)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A redesign of the publication backend for eXist-DB: 2025–present</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
    <para>The initial digital publication of Women Writers Online in 1999 showcased Renaissance
      Women Online (RWO), a subset of WWO representing works originally published between 1500 and
      1670. RWO consisted of two complementary forms of interface. At the time, WWP Electronic
      Publications Editor Paul Caton described these interfaces:<blockquote>
        <para>A plain HTML version allows relatively quick access but no searching, which suits the
          user who wants simply to read or look over a work. The other form uses Inso Corporation’s
          DynaWeb software, which dynamically translates an SGML version to HTML for the browser
          while retaining access to the SGML; this allows users to perform searches on the
          SGML-encoded texts, at the cost of somewhat slower access.</para>
      </blockquote> (<xref linkend="caton1998"/>)</para>
    <para>The initial WWO and RWO collections were further defined by robust search with
      keywords-in-context; tables of contents for user navigation within a given work; as well as
      contextual materials such as short summaries, scholarly introductions to works, and essays on
      topics and collections.<footnote>
        <para>Later, these contextual essays were republished in Women Writers in Context.</para>
      </footnote></para>
    <para>By 2003 the WWP began seeking a successor to DynaWeb for both technical and administrative
      reasons. The Inso Corporation had been bought by another company, which altered both the level
      of support and also the license terms in ways that made it increasingly untenable to use
      DynaWeb for a small academic project. In 2004 the project began experimenting with Philologic,
      developed by Mark Olsen at the University of Chicago, and in 2005, the WWP released an updated 
      WWO running on Philologic. Philologic placed its emphasis on speed and power; it was
      database-driven and selective in its indexing, so that it was able to provide very fast search
      results as well as context-sensitive searching. Its search also included fuzzy matching, which
      made it adept at handling the highly variable spelling in older WWO texts. This system served
      us well for several years, but by 2011 the project was seeking a more modern XML framework
      that would support more flexible experimentation with interface, responding to the significant
      expansion of interface paradigms as “digital humanities” became a widespread academic
      domain.</para>
    <para>Starting in 2012, Women Writers Online was served out of <link xlink:href="https://xtf.cdlib.org/">XTF</link> (eXtensible Text Framework),
      a Java- and XSLT-based publication system created by the California Digital Library. The WWP
      staff heavily customized XTF's stylesheets in order to produce indexable versions of the WWO
      documents, as well as HTML representations for display. On the front end, Women Writers Online
      was reimagined as a dynamic, three-pane interface, with users seamlessly flowing from browsing
      to searching to reading a document. Within this design, WWO offered users a sense that
      searching/filtering, visualizing, and reading are really three manifestations or framings of
      the same thing, at different levels of scale. This approach contrasted strongly with the
      traditional (at the time) search model in which users would first specify a set of search
      parameters and then execute a search to receive results—with the need to go back to the start
      of the process if the results were not what the user wanted. (A few years later, Stephen
      Ramsay’s essay on “The Hermeneutics of Screwing Around” [<xref linkend="ramsay2010"/>]
      captured the element of play and exploration that such “pipeline” systems foreclose.) By
      searching and filtering across WWO, one can “read” the corpus as a whole as a spread of dots
      on a timeline, or as a list of matching search results — keywords in context for multiple WWO
      documents. One can then focus in on a more specific area (e.g. a specific genre or time
      period) and finally on a specific text. Although this interface doesn’t fully implement this
      idea, it introduces it and makes it possible.</para>
    <para>Around the same time, the WWP universe began to expand beyond Women Writers Online. The
      WWP produced Women Writers in Context (WWiC), a collection of modern scholarly essays
      providing crucial background for the documents, authors, and genres found in WWO. Later, Women
      Writers in Review (WWiR) made contemporary reviews of WWO authors’ works available, and
      referenceable from WWO itself. These two endeavors aim to flesh out the milieu of WWO authors.
      The sites link to each other to aid users’ exploration, but are not integrated directly into a
      single interface. Unlike WWO, the sister sites are public resources, available to anyone,
      regardless of WWO subscription. Their documents are lightly customized TEI, much more geared
      towards supporting collection-level metadata, presentation and quick publication turnaround
      than research artifacts. Their interfaces in turn prioritize findability and the ability of
      users to follow connections between resources.</para>
    <para>Women Writers: Intertextual Networks (WW:IN) sought to compile significant amounts of data from
      TEI sources for exploration and research. The data was drawn from two primary sources: (1) the
      WWO documents, which were marked-up to add references to (2) entries within a separate,
      TEI-encoded bibliography. Unlike its sister sites, however, the WW:IN interface was designed
      to do much more work on the server-side, with Javascript limited to functions that would make
      the site more interactive. An EXPath application, housed in the XML database <link xlink:href="https://www.exist-db.org/exist/apps/homepage/index.html">eXist-DB</link>, would apply users’
      desired filters to return customized datasets in full HTML responses. The same API that
      returned JSON or XML would also serve out the webpages, putting far less pressure on users’
      devices.</para>
    <para>This succession of different tools has been challenging, in that it has required periodic
      episodes of substantial redevelopment. However, those transitions have also given the project
      an important push at each point to rethink how the interface could best serve readers and best
      express the capacities of the data. And they also prevented the project from experiencing the
      publication platform as a fixed horizon of possibility to which the data should adapt.
      Instead, the project has developed an extensive set of pre-publication processes that take the
      WWP’s source data and transform it as necessary for the specific foibles and requirements of
      the current tool.</para>
    <para>For example, like many TEI projects, the WWP makes frequent use of intra-word markup in
      Women Writers Online. One example of this is the WWP’s <code>&lt;vuji></code> tag, which is
      used to encode letterforms commonly substituted for each other in early typesetting, such as
      an “j” represented with an “i”. The <code>&lt;vuji></code> element is a useful shorthand for a
      TEI <code>&lt;choice></code>.</para>
      <figure>
        <programlisting language="xml">in&lt;choice>&lt;orig>i&lt;/orig>&lt;reg>j&lt;/reg>&lt;/choice>urious</programlisting>
        <caption>
          <para>The word “injurious” transcribed using <link xlink:href="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CO.html#COEDREG">standard TEI elements <code>&lt;choice></code>, <code>&lt;orig></code>, and <code>&lt;reg></code></link>. The encoding indicates that the word was originally printed with an “i” where modern readers would expect a “j”.</para>
        </caption>
      </figure>
      <figure xml:id="injurious-vuji">
        <programlisting language="xml">in&lt;vuji>i&lt;/vuji>urious</programlisting>
        <caption>
          <para>The same word, transcribed using the WWP’s shorthand element <code>&lt;vuji></code>. Only the originally-printed letter is transcribed. When encoded this way, the letter “i” will only ever be regularized to the letter “j” (and vice versa).</para>
        </caption>
      </figure>
    <para>XML publishing software consistently treats element tags as distinct words. Our
      pre-publication stylesheets adapt our markup as needed to avoid this problem. Originally, the
      original letterform represented in <code>&lt;vuji></code> was converted to its modern
      equivalent, and the tag itself was removed.</para>
    <para>More recently, when WWO introduced a feature allowing users to toggle between modern and
      original typography, the pre-publication stylesheets retained <code>&lt;vuji></code>.
      When the TEI was transformed into HTML, <code>&lt;vuji></code> became an HTML <code>&lt;span></code>, and its text content flipped to the modern version.</para>
      <figure>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="img/Bal2026clar041601_injurious.png" width="700"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Screenshot of <emphasis>Jane Anger Her Protection for Women</emphasis>, as it first appears in Women Writers Online. The word “injurious” has been highlighted. The browser’s Inspector tool shows that the letter “j” is encoded in HTML as <code>&lt;span class="icor icor-reg">j&lt;/span></code>.</para>
        </caption>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="img/Bal2026clar041602_iniurious.png" width="850"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Screenshot of <emphasis>Jane Anger Her Protection for Women</emphasis> in Women Writers Online, with the “Show original typographical features” preference toggled on. The highlighted word now reads “iniurious”, as it did in the 1589 publication. The browser’s Inspector tool shows that the letter “j” was changed to <code>&lt;span class="icor icor-reg" data-wwo-orig="i">i&lt;/span></code> in the Document Object Model.</para>
        </caption>
      </figure>
      <para>Unfortunately, the new feature had the unfortunate side effect of reducing XTF’s ability to index and search older documents, because a
      single word would be broken up by tags.
        <figure>
        <programlisting>in j urious</programlisting>
        <caption>
          <para>A plain-text representation of how XTF would parse the word “injurious” as encoded in <xref linkend="injurious-vuji"/>. XTF would introduce spaces in place of the start and end tags of <code>&lt;vuji></code>.</para>
        </caption>
      </figure>
In order to retain both the toggle feature and the collection’s searchability, Women
      Writers Online was moved out of the XTF platform and into an eXist-DB database. While
      eXist-DB’s Lucene index also treats tags as word boundaries by default, eXist does provide a way to
      define elements like <code>&lt;vuji></code> as <link xlink:href="https://www.exist-db.org/exist/apps/doc/lucene#inline">“inline,”</link> or, implying no word break. As such,
      a search in eXist for the word “injurious” will lead to <emphasis>Jane Anger
        Her Protection For Women</emphasis>, where XTF would have come up short.</para>
    <para>Importantly, while the code for the WWO site was updated and adapted for use in eXist, the WWO documents themselves stayed the same.
      The relationship between the markup and the publication tool is thus very indirect. The
      markup represents a durable, evolving expression of our analysis of the source texts, based on
      the project’s editorial principles and expectations about the kinds of research questions this
      data should support in the very long term. The publication platform, on the other hand,
      represents a particular manifestation of the potential of that data, under particular
      circumstances of resource constraints and technological capability. Even in the WWP’s other
      publications (see <xref linkend="wwp-pubs"/>) where the encoding is more deliberately
      aimed at producing a specific kind of outcome, the source markup remains tool-agnostic and
      could be published through varied systems to produce varied user experiences.</para>
    <para>Read broadly, this history reveals several important points. First, the lifespan of
      monolithic tools was comparatively short: the first two iterations of Women Writers Online
      (DynaWeb and Philologic) each lasted about six years, whereas our current system has evolved
      more or less gracefully over the past 14 years with incremental modifications. Second,
      although the WWP never “coded to the tool” in the sense of altering our data to match what a
      given tool could or could not do, our publication tools have definitely put their stamp on
      what Women Writers Online as a publication could express about that data. The centrality of
      the keywords-in-context display in DynaWeb, the excellent division-level context-sensitive searching in
      Philologic, and the dynamic relationship between global and local reading views in the current
      interface all reflect, at a macroscopic level, the platform’s understanding of what “XML
      publishing” means (inflected as well by the WWP’s own intentions for the data).</para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Project sustainability</title>
    <para>In July 2023, the Women Writers Project staff held a retreat to discuss plans for the next
      ten years of the WWP — what would the Project need in order to continue on indefinitely, in
      areas such as staffing, technology, and administration. The retreat focused on staff analysis of
      various aspects of the Project. Our markup and publication processes seemed stable for the
      moment, but analysis revealed that these systems were potentially at risk to events for which
      we had no contingency or recovery plan.</para>
    <para>For example, many of the WWP’s web resources are
      dependent on eXist-DB. For years, the eXist database had its own divergent implementations of XQuery
      standards, such as XPath functions, XQuery Update, and output serialization.<footnote>
        <para>See the <link
            xlink:href="https://www.exist-db.org/exist/apps/doc/xquery#unsupported-features">“XQuery
            in eXist-db” documentation page</link> for a list of XQuery features currently unsupported by
          eXist, and features which have eXist-specific implementations.</para>
      </footnote> eXist-specific code requires
      eXist-specific knowledge to use and maintain it — a high barrier to entry and a high barrier
      to exiting. Northeastern’s Digital Scholarship Group — of which the Women Writers Project is a part — had
          already adopted BaseX as its XML database of choice for TEI and other XML projects, due to
          BaseX’s lightweight footprint, excellent documentation, and adherence to the XQuery
          standard. At this time, the WWP is the only DSG project which uses eXist. The WWP’s dependency on eXist is also a dependence on continued staffing with
      eXist-specific skills.</para>
    <note>
      <para>To their credit, eXist’s development team has also identified specification compliance as a significant goal, and they have been making incremental progress since at least 2016.<footnote>
          <para>In a 2019 eXist issue thread, Joe Wicentowski posted <link xlink:href="https://github.com/eXist-db/exist/issues/2626#issuecomment-480319383">this summary of eXist-specific functions</link> which were deprecated in eXist version 4, and which would be removed in version 5 — many in favor of spec-compliant versions. Wicentowski had been tracking <link xlink:href="https://gist.github.com/joewiz/acb0558f078c0576a5e7?permalink_comment_id=1568552#gistcomment-1568552">eXist’s compliance with the Functions and Operators specification</link> since 2015, as well as helping the team improve eXist.</para>
      </footnote> As we prepared to revise our paper in June 2026, they announced a beta version of 7.0.0, the next major version of eXist — and with it, a 90% success rate against 31,815 tests, a commendable increase from version 6.4.1’s 80% success rate. (<xref linkend="exist7beta"/>)</para>
    </note>
    <para>By the close of the retreat, we decided it would be prudent to familiarize ourselves with
      the outcomes of the <link xlink:href="https://endings.uvic.ca/">Endings Project</link>. The Endings Project was convened in 2016 by the
      University of Victoria’s Humanities Computing and Media Centre (HCMC), with the goal of
      developing methods towards the longevity of their digital artifacts. In 2018, the team
      released their first version of the “Endings Principles for Digital Longevity” (<xref linkend="endings"/>). These principles describe the foundations of a digital project which can be
      used, cited, reproduced, and archived. By building for open use, the Endings Project argues,
      the digital products are far more likely to be reused and maintained, and thus, more likely to
      survive.</para>
    <para>The Endings Project promotes the use of standalone, static websites, with no server-side
      processing or backend components. The HTML markup is not programmatically built out after the
      page loads; all content is available and all dependencies are satisfied simply by accessing
      the file. (<xref
        linkend="endings"/>) This greatly aids those who intentionally set out to archive the project materials,
      such as a digital repository or the Internet Archive’s Wayback Machine. The static site
      approach also makes it easy for researchers and other users to become casual archivists. It is
      not necessary to use extensions or software to generate a <link xlink:href="https://iipc.github.io/warc-specifications/specifications/warc-format/warc-1.1-annotated/">WARC file</link> from the page; saving the
      page as an HTML file is enough to obtain your own working copy.</para>
    <!-- Ash: need to explain here that making static sites makes it easier for classic web archiving to do its thing, and for us to be able to hand the products off to someone else to host -->
    <para>Though the WWP puts much of our emphasis on the markup — without which, there would be no
      publication — the Endings Project counsels against considering our data alone as enough for
      project preservation. Dynamic “products” such as website interfaces are “arguably the most
      recognizable and least preservable part of a digital project” (<xref linkend="holmes2023a"/>).
      A website is the most public expression of a project’s data, and an invitation for users to
      participate in the products’ use and reuse. <blockquote>
        <para>Just as we offer repurposable XML versions of our documents, we try to provide HTML
          pages which can also be pulled out of the project and reused easily. While TEI XML is a
          widely-used and trusted archival format for digital scholarly work, compared with HTML,
          its audience is tiny. As we have noted elsewhere, the many billions of HTML pages already
          created constitute many times the number of printed books produced in the entire history
          of humanity, and the variety of purposes already served by HTML (not only websites but
          mobile applications, archival storage, and others) will ensure that if anything from the
          current era of digital communication survives, it will be HTML. So our HTML is more likely
          to be reused than our XML in the long term.</para>
      </blockquote> (<xref linkend="holmes2023b"/>).</para>
    <para>In our pursuit of maintainability, the WWP is working towards greater synthesis between
      markup, documentation, and website, especially for Women Writers Online. The interface can
      make greater use of the markup, for instance. We have plans to add more user control over what
      they see in the interface, such as a toggle to show the lineation of the original publication.
      With careful design, the interface can demonstrate the capabilities of the markup, as well as
      catering to those who just want a clean, readable text. We also intend to make it easier for
      users to download the WWO TEI files.</para>
    <para>However, the highest priority for the WWP is refactoring our current publication processes
      for sustainability, and to produce static websites. Step one is to migrate our apps from eXist
      to BaseX. Because the code will be specification-standard XQuery, its maintenance and upkeep can be undertaken by more people. We will document the
      process of publication via BaseX and automate as much of the publication processes as
      possible.</para>
    <para>For Women Writers in Review and Women Writers in Context, step two will be to shift away from single-page Javascript applications
      and towards giving the user a complete HTML page on request.<footnote>
        <para>Women Writers in Review and Women Writers in Context each have a single index page. On
          page load, their <link
            xlink:href="https://backbonejs.org/">Backbone.js</link> apps request and consume data
          from the XQuery API in eXist. That data is used to construct a web page to match the
          user’s request. As a user navigates one of these sites, its Javascript application builds
          and rebuilds the Document Object Model within the browser, adjusting the URL address as
          new “pages” load.</para>
      </footnote> We will adjust the site for web accessibility and universal design features,
      limiting Javascript to facilitating interaction. This will also require updating existing
      URLs, since Backbone.js applications previously maintained the browser’s history once the user
      entered the site. Women Writers Online already went through this process during the migration
      to eXist.</para>
    <para>Step three is to generate static HTML. The current hope is that we will use the migrated
      XQuery code to generate HTML out of BaseX. Each page will be saved as a separate HTML file, in
      directories mapping onto the URL paths. When a user requests a web page, the server responds
      with the static HTML, rather than initiating a request to BaseX. We may still incorporate
      search through BaseX.</para>
    <para>The WWP is at the beginning of step one. This step mostly consists of rewriting XQuery
      code so that a BaseX environment can produce the same JSON output that eXist currently does.
      However, where possible, we are also trying to make it easier to accomplish steps two and
      three. For example, some web content generated in Javascript can be extricated and placed in
      either an XQuery response, or the HTML page.</para>
    <para>Throughout the process, we are also working to make our web content more accessible. For
      example, the Women Writers Online interface includes a standard “Search” feature, implemented
      as a form. When a user clicked the “Search” button, the Backbone.js application would prevent
      the browser from navigating the user to a new page with their query parameters applied.
      Instead, the application requested the search results and populated the current page with
      them. From a sighted user’s standpoint, this was convenient and useful. From a blind user’s
      perspective, however, nothing would happen after they clicked the button; the WWO application
      did not alert them that the page had changed. If the request had been allowed to go through
      the browser, a screen reader would have informed the blind user that they had gone to a new
      page as a result of their request, with the search results found within the content of the
      page.</para>
    <para>By removing usability barriers such as low color contrast, we extend our invitation for
      use and reuse further, to people of all abilities. And by preferring semantic HTML markup over
      CSS formatting, we bring the full semantics of the markup into focus.</para>
  </section>
  
  <!-- Ash: Bring static sites into conversation with enriched data and interfaces 
       Engaging readers with the static site powered interface
       Loop back around from process to impact, synthesis
  -->
  <section>
    <!-- Both: stronger conclusion -->
    <title>Synthesis</title>
    <para>Markup and tools have co-evolved</para>
    <para>It turns out that they really are two dialogic/dialectical parts of the same modeling ecology; tools not just a kind of sea anchor or gaudy temptation, but something that also contributes to our understanding of what a model of text is</para>
    <para>…explore the consequences of this idea</para>
    <para>Next steps, research questions, Onward!</para>
  </section>
  
  <!-- Could include an appendix timeline of WWP encoding/publication history -->
  <appendix xml:id="wwp-pubs">
    <title>Women Writers Project Publications</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><link xlink:href="https://wwp.northeastern.edu/wwo/">Women Writers Online</link> (WWO)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The WWP’s flagship publication, a collection of transcribed works by women which were originally published between 1526 and 1850.</para>
          <para>WWO was first published in 1999. “<xref linkend="evolution-of-toolsets"/>” provides details about WWO’s publication history.</para>
          <para>Access is limited to subscribers.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><link xlink:href="https://wwp.northeastern.edu/context/">Women Writers in Context</link> (WWiC)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A collection of modern “exhibits” — scholarly publications which provide context and create connections between works in the WWO textbase.</para>
          <para>The WWP’s first call for submissions went online in March 2009.</para><!-- When was WWiC first published? Was it always in eXist? ~Ash -->
          <para>Open access.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><link xlink:href="https://wwp.northeastern.edu/review/">Women Writers in Review</link> (WWiR)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The WWP’s collection of 18th- and 19th-century reviews and other texts which respond to the works of early women writers.</para>
          <para>WWiR is the product of “<link xlink:href="https://wwp.northeastern.edu/research/projects/reception/">Cultures of Reception</link>,” a 2011–2015 research project funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities.</para>
          <para>Open access.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><link xlink:href="https://wwp.northeastern.edu/intertextual-networks">Women Writers: Intertextual Networks</link> (WW:IN)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A bibliography and extracts from WWO, surfacing the sources of quotations, allusions, and citations in the Women Writers Online textbase.</para>
          <para>WW:IN came out of the grant-funded research project <link xlink:href="https://wwp.northeastern.edu/research/projects/intertextuality/index.html">Intertextual Networks</link>, which began in 2016 by augmenting the WWO markup. WW:IN was first published in 2022. Since its launch, it has been taken down periodically due to overzealous scraping.</para>
          <para>Open access.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </appendix>
  
  <bibliography>
    <title>Works Cited</title>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="caton1998" xreflabel="Caton 1998">Caton, Paul. “Putting Renaissance Women Online.” <emphasis>WWP
        Newsletter</emphasis>, vol. 4, no. 1, 1998, Women Writers Project. <link
       
        xlink:href="https://wwp.northeastern.edu/about/history/archive/newsletter/vol04num01/RWO041.html"
        >wwp.northeastern.edu/about/history/archive/newsletter/vol04num01/RWO041.html</link>.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="endings" xreflabel="Endings Principles 2023">Endings Project Team. “Endings Principles for Digital Longevity.” Version 2.2.1.
        <emphasis>The Endings Project</emphasis>, University of Victoria, 3 Mar. 2023. <link
       
        xlink:href="https://endings.uvic.ca/principles.html"
        >endings.uvic.ca/principles.html</link>.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="exist7beta" xreflabel="eXist-db release 7.0.0-beta3">eXist-db authors. “Release eXist-7.0.0-beta3.” eXist-db/exist repository, 2 Jun. 2026. <link xlink:href="https://github.com/eXist-db/exist/releases/tag/eXist-7.0.0-beta3">github.com/eXist-db/exist/releases/tag/eXist-7.0.0-beta3</link>.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="holmes2023a" xreflabel="Holmes, Jenstad, and Huculak 2023">Holmes, Martin, Janelle Jenstad, and J. Matthew Huculak. “Introduction to Special
      Issue: Project Resiliency in the Digital Humanities.” <emphasis>Digital Humanities
        Quarterly</emphasis>, vol. 17, no. 1, 2023, <link
        xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.63744/g7c3rkvm5bzr"
        >https://doi.org/10.63744/g7c3rkvm5bzr</link>.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="holmes2023b" xreflabel="Holmes and Takeda 2023">Holmes, Martin, and Joey Takeda. “From Tamagotchis to Pet Rocks: On Learning to
      Love Simplicity through the Endings Principles.” <emphasis>Digital Humanities
        Quarterly</emphasis>, vol. 17, no. 1, 2023, <link
        xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.63744/dr2uaqdau4tz"
        >https://doi.org/10.63744/dr2uaqdau4tz</link>.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="melson2010" xreflabel="Melson and Flanders 2010">Melson, John, and Julia Flanders. “Not Just One of Your Holiday Games: Names and
      Name Encoding in the Women Writers Project Textbase.” Women Writers Project, Jan. 2010, <link
       
        xlink:href="https://wwp.northeastern.edu/research/publications/reports/neh_2008/WWP_Names_White_Paper.pdf"
        >wwp.northeastern.edu/research/publications/reports/neh_2008/WWP_Names_White_Paper.pdf</link>.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="ramsay2010" xreflabel="Ramsay 2010">Ramsay, Stephen. “The Hermeneutics of Screwing Around; or What You Do with a
      Million Books.” In <emphasis>Pastplay: Teaching and Learning History with
        Technology</emphasis>, edited by Kevin Kee, 111-20. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press,
      2014. Originally presented as a talk at Brown University, April 17, 2010.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="teip5about" xreflabel="TEI Guidelines, “About These Guidelines”">TEI Consortium. “iv. About These Guidelines.” In <emphasis>TEI: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</emphasis>, P5 Version 4.11.0, 18 Feb. 2026. <link xlink:href="https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/AB.html#ABTEI">tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/AB.html#ABTEI</link>.</bibliomixed>
  </bibliography>
</article>
